Abraham: So how does Cyber
crime affect the individual?
As individuals we can have
our finances and social status
heavily impacted by cyber crime.
Unsolicited emails and texts and
those often pertaining to be from
our own bank or the Inland Revenue
can have consequences when interacted
with which may be financial.
Once details have been unwittingly
given, the cyber criminals have
access to more than just our details,
they can access bank accounts and
commit crimes using our identity.
This can then expand into our social
media circles or work-based contacts.
Phones and smart technology around
the home can be hacked and taken
control of with the opportunity
for being surveilled by cameras.
Having 'up to date’ antimalware software
and making sure all programs are up to
date can help to keep systems secure.
Also taking extra precautions like having
good password protection, cautious when
giving out details online, only accessing
secure sites, keeping phones and storage
devices safe and away from prying eyes and
being careful with any documentation that
may have details on it and destroying it.
Nicole: Let’s now look at
how it can affect Businesses.
Cybercrime can devastate a company’s
finances and reputation quickly
or can cause a great deal of
disruption to an organisation.
In the long term it can cause irreparable
financial or brand damage, or even
threaten an individual’s way of life.
Companies need to realise what a
threat cyber crime is and to stop
their business falling victim to
the cyber criminals should invest
in reliable cyber security services.
A DDoS cyber attack involves a network
being flooded with excessive traffic
causing it to shut down and becoming
unavailable to legitimate users.
Hacking involves the cybercriminal
in trying to take advantage
of vulnerabilities in a
company’s software and systems.
Hackers will ask for a ransom to end
the attack, however by using trusted
and reliable technology service
providers, increasing bandwidth, and
designing systems to scale with traffic
using the cloud this can be prevented.
There is also a significant impact to
the business from regulatory bodies.
An example of this would be British
Airways who were fined £20 million
one of the highest under GDPR by the
ICO for their lack of due diligence
that led to the compromise of
429,612 staff and customer details.
Abraham: The effects of cybercrime
can be minimised by businesses making
employees aware and wary of downloading
attachments or clicking on links
to reset passwords without knowing
exactly who they have come from or
checking their authenticity directly.
Personal information and contact details
should not be given freely, so as to
give access to hackers and scammers.
Businesses should also limit the amount of
information they put out on their website.
Passwords should be long, complex, and
original for each individual account.
They should not be easy to identify from
personal information, for example, not the
name of a child or pet, or based on the
month or season of the year ‘Summer2021’.
These sorts of password relatedly come
up on the list of most common passwords.
To minimise insider attacks all
data storage should be encrypted
and software should be updated
regularly to maintain security.
Companies can also enforce two-factor
authentication for all their user
accounts so that attackers are less
likely to be able to gain access
even with the right credentials.
Nicole: So how are nations affected?
Nation state attacks are
usually thought of as highly
complex, and technology based.
However social engineering is commonly
used to convince individuals to download
malware to create security breaches.
“Spear Phishing' attacks are often
used to infiltrate, inserting
malware which may remain dormant
until triggered by an outside agency
making it difficult to guard against.
State-backed actors are responsible
for gaining access to computer
networks around the world.
Countries like China seem intent on
committing large scale espionage even
though as part of the G20 they agreed not
to conduct or support cyber enabled theft
of intellectual property or personal data.
In the UK The National Cyber Security
Centre [NCSC] supports the government
giving advice to organisations affected
by state run cyber intrusions stealing
trade secrets such as those by the Chinese
Ministry of State Security [MSS] in 2018.
Abraham: To guard against these often
changing and increasingly sophisticated
attacks, organisations must have a
multi-layered approach to their cyber
security [referred to as “defence in
depth”], creating nation state threat
risk models and educating employees on
being hyper aware of nation state attacks.
They also need to be constantly aware of
the threat and training should be ongoing.